RG 120, National Society, United States Daughters of 1812
Connecticut State Library
National Society, United States Daughters of 1812 records
1769-2003
Connecticut State Library
National Society, United States Daughters of 1812
11.5 cubic feet
The National Society, United States Daughters of 1812, was organized January 8, 1892. To become eligible for membership, a prospective member was required to trace her genealogy directly to an ancestor who had served in the United States military or civil service between 1784 and 1815. Chief among the Society's purposes was the dissemination of knowledge of American history. The Connecticut Society was organized March 2, 1906.
RG120
Multiple
Historical Note
The National Society, United States Daughters of 1812, was organized January 8, 1892. To become eligible for membership, a prospective member was required to trace her genealogy directly to an ancestor who had served in the United States military or civil service between 1784 and 1815. Chief among the Society's purposes was the dissemination of knowledge of American history. Concrete ways in which this objective was pursued were "preserving documents and relics, marking historic spots, recording family histories and traditions, … [and] urging…Congress to compile and publish authentic records of men in civil, military and naval service from 1784 to 1815 (Hartford Courant, July 19, 1936.)
The Connecticut Society of U.S. Daughters of 1812 was organized March 2, 1906, by Mrs. Charles H. Pinney, who became its first president. The Connecticut branch participated actively in the national society becoming particularly prominent when a Hartford woman, Mrs. Clarence F.R. Jenne, became the national president in 1918.
Scope and Content
Series 1, National Society includes newsletters, 1905-1963; bound proceedings of the Associate Council, 1932-1958; scrapbooks, 1936-1954, that include newspaper and magazine clippings, announcements of meetings, rosters, historian's reports, photographs, etc.; histories, circa 1942, are typescripts that include "History of National Society, United States Daughters of 1812, State of Connecticut," by Mrs. Henry Wheeler Warren, circa 1942; and a "History of Administration of Mrs. Clarence F.R. Jenne," by the same author, undated; reports, 1922-1923, that include the Associate Council Annual Messages and Reports for 1922 and 1923; and the Report of Historian National, 1938 and 1939; publications; and historical manuscripts, 1769-1922. Series 2, Connecticut Society includes the charter, 1906; minutes, 1939-1963; programs, 1935-1968; papers, 1935-1990; and scrapbooks, circa 1907-2003.
Index Terms
Organizations:
National Society, United States Daughters of 1812; National Society, United States Daughters of 1812. Connecticut Society
Subjects:
Connecticut -- History -- War of 1812 -- Societies, etc.; National Society, United States Daughters of 1812 -- Records and correspondence; National Society, United States Daughters of 1812. Connecticut Society -- Records and correspondence; United States -- History -- War of 1812 -- Societies, etc.
Document Types:
Charters; Correspondence; Manuscripts (document genre); Minutes; Newsletters; Proceedings; Programs; Reports; Scrapbooks
Restrictions on Access
See the policy.
Container List
- Series 1. National Society, 1769-1963; T001453
  - 1. Newsletters, 1905 December 8 - 1963 March
    - 1906 December - 1915 April (Volume Item 1)
    - 1915 June - 1919 March (Volume Item 2)
    - 1919 June - 1923 March (Volume Item 3)
    - 1923 June - 1927 March (Volume Item 4)
    - 1927 June - 1931 March (Volume Item 5)
    - 1931 June - 1934 March (Volume Item 6)
    - 1934 July - 1937 March (Volume Item 7)
    - 1937 July - 1940 March (Volume Item 8)
    - 1940 July - 1943 March (Volume Item 9)
    - 1943 July - 1946 March (Volume Item 10)
    - 1946 July - 1949 March (Volume Item 11)
    - 1949 July - 1952 March (Volume Item 12)
    - 1952 July - 1955 March (Volume Item 13)
    - 1955 July - 1958 March (Volume Item 14)
    - 1958 July - 1963 March (Volume Item 15)
  - 2. Proceedings of the Associate Council, 1932-1958
    - 1932 April - 1936 April (Volume Item 16)
    - 1937 April - 1941 April (Volume Item 17)
    - 1942 April - 1949 April (Volume Item 18)
    - 1956 April (Volume Item 19)
    - 1957 April (Volume Item 20)
    - 1958 April (Volume Item 21)
  - 3. Scrapbooks, 1936-1954 (Volume Item 22)
  - 4. Histories, circa 1942 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - 5. Reports, 1922-1923, 1938-1939 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - 6. Program, dedication of memorial tablet at State Capitol, 1935 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - 7. Publications, 1933-1947 (Box 23)
    - Welles, Edwin Stanley, ed. Inspection Returns of the 5th Co., 6th Regiment of Conn. Militia, 1813-1814. Hartford, 1933. (Box 23)
    - Miller, Francesca Falk. "1812": The Story of the War of 1812 in Song and Story. Chicago: Bauman, 1935. (Box 23)
    - History of the National Society United States Daughters of 1812, State of Georgia, 1901-1942. 1942. (Box 23)
    - Tennessee Soldiers in the War of 1812. Vol 1. Tennessee Society, United States Daughters of 1812, 1947. (Box 23)
  - 8. Historical manuscripts, 1769-1922 (Box 24)
    - Abijah B. Curtis papers connected with his service in the War of 1812, 1813-1814 (Box 24)
    - Leonard Fox pension papers, War of 1812, 1878 (Box 24)
    - Muster roll for the 2nd Company in Col. John Satter's Regiment, 1813 June 8 (Box 24)
    - Names of the soldiers who were at New London on a tour of duty, undated (Box 24)
    - Dwight R. Tyler papers connected with his service in the War of 1812, 1854, 1878 (Box 24)
    - Widows pension for Mary K. Tyler, 1880 (Box 24)
    - Joshua R. Warren papers connected with his service in the War of 1812, 1777-1835 (Box 24)
    - Deeds of land in Guilford, Conn. purchased by Benhamin Chittenden, 1785-1815 (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1769-1814; 2 envelopes (Box 24)
    - "Our Real Daughters" photographs and biographical sketches of Daughters of Soldiers of the War of 1812-1815, circa 1850-1922; 1 binder (Box 24)
  - 9. Francis Edward Brownell collection, 1932 (Box 25)
    Correspondence & miscellaneous papers.
  - 10. Short sketch of the Life of Major Felix Ansart (Box 25)
  - 11. Miscellaneous newspaper articles, 2 folders (Box 25)
  - 12. Roll of Honor, World War 1914-1919 (Box 25)
  - 13. Catalog of Books on Naval History and the War of 1812 (Box 25)
  - 14. "General Entry Book of American Prisoners of War at Quebec" (War of 1812) (Box Item 26)
- Series 2. Connecticut Society, 1906-2003
  - 2005-001
    - Charter, 1906 March 2 (Box Oversize box)
  - 2005-017
    - Annual report of president, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Historical papers, 1912-1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Meetings, 1966-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Minutes, 1939-1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Minutes of executive board, 1943-1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Papers, 1950-1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 6-12)
    - Papers, miscellaneous, 1935-1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Photographs, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Programs, 1935-1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Publication of National Society, 1915, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Rituals, 1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Rosters, 1940-1985 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    - Scrapbook, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Watkins, Walter Kendall. The Defence of Boston in the War of 1812-15, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Scrapbooks
      - circa 1985-1994, 1 volume (Box 3)
      - circa 1958-1978, 1 volume (Box 3)
      - circa 1919-2003, 1 binder (Box 4)
      - circa 1907-1994, 1 binder (Box 5)